Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...
Junction Investment Series
Don Deную
Daniel Lares
Ron Seabrook
Quiaka
John Carter
Claire P ситуVELO
Lut perfect
Paul Priok
Henderson
claims of moral desert on the one hand,
and of entitlements to legitimate expectations on the other.
Rawls argued that it's a mistake to think
that distributive justice is a matter of moral desert,
a matter of rewarding people according to their virtue.
Today we're going to explore that question of moral desert
and its relation to distributive justice,
not in connection with income and wealth,
but in its connection with opportunities,
with hiring decisions and admission standards.
And so we turn to the case of affirmative action.
You read about the case of Cheryl Hopwood.
She applied for admission to
the University of Texas Law School.
Cheryl Hopwood had worked her way through high school.
She didn't come from an affluent family.
She put herself through community college
and California State University at Sacramento.
She achieved a 3.8 grade point average there,
later moved to Texas, became a resident,
took the law school admissions test,
did pretty well on that,
and she applied to the University of Texas Law School.
She was turned down.
She was turned down at a
time when the University of Texas
was using an affirmative action admissions policy,
a policy that took into account race and ethnic background.
The University of Texas said,
40% of the population of Texas is
made up of African Americans and Mexican Americans.
It's important that we, as a law school,
have a diverse student body.
And so we are going to take
into account not only grades and test scores,
but also the demographic makeup of our class,
including our students.
We're going to take into account race and ethnic profile.
The result, and this is what Hopwood complained about,
the result of that policy is that some applicants
to the University of Texas Law
School with a lower academic index,
which includes grades and test scores,
than hers were admitted, and she was turned down.
She said, she argued, I'm just
being turned down because I'm white.
If I weren't, if I were
a member of a minority group,
with my grades and test
scores, I would have been admitted.
And the statistics, the admissions statistics
that came out in the trial,
confirmed that African American and
Mexican American applicants that year
who had her grades and test scores were admitted.
It went to federal court.
Now, put aside the law, let's consider
it from the standpoint of justice and morality.
Is it fair or is it unfair?
Does Cheryl Hopwood have a case, a legitimate complaint?
Were her rights violated by the
admissions policy of the law school?
How many say, how many
would rule for the law school
and say that it was
just to consider race and ethnicity
as a factor in admissions?
How many would rule for Cheryl
Hopwood and say her rights were violated?
So here we have a pretty even split.
All right, now I want to
hear from a defender of Cheryl Hopwood.
Yes.
You're basing something on that's an arbitrary factor.
You know, Cheryl couldn't control
the fact that she was white
or not in a minority group.
She was a minority.
And therefore, you know, it's not as
if it was like a test score
that she worked hard to try
and show that she could, you know,
put that out there, you know, that
she had no control over her race.
Good.
And what's your name?
Bree.
Okay, Bree.
Stay right there.
Now let's find someone who has an answer for Bree.
Yes.
There are discrepancies in the educational system.
And majority of the time, I
know this in New York City,
the schools that minorities go
to are not as well funded.
Are not as well supplied as white schools.
And so there is going to be a discrepancy naturally
between minorities and between whites
if they go to better schools.
And they will not do as well on
exams because they haven't had as much help
because of a worse school system.
All right.
Let me just interrupt you.
Tell me your name.
Anisha.
Anisha, you're pointing out that
minority kids may have gone,
in some cases, to a minority school.
And that's because they didn't
get the same educational opportunities
to schools that didn't give
them the same educational opportunity
as kids from affluent families.
Yes.
And so the test scores they got
may actually not represent their true potential.
Because they didn't receive the same kind
of help that they might have received
had they gone to a school with better funding.
Good.
All right.
Anisha has raised the point
that colleges still should choose,
for the greatest academic scholarly promise,
to take into account the different
meaning of the test scores and grades
in the light of educational disadvantage in the background.
But in reading the test scores and grades,
they should take into account the different meaning
those tests and grades have
in the light of educational disadvantage in the background.
So that's one argument
in defense of affirmative action.
Anisha's argument.
Correcting for the effects
of unequal preparation.
Educational disadvantage.
There are other arguments.
Suppose, just to identify whether
there is a competing principle here,
suppose there are two candidates
who did equally well
on the tests and grades,
both of whom went to first-rate schools.
Two candidates.
Among those candidates,
would it be unfair
for the college or university,
for Harvard,
to say,
we still want diversity
along racial and ethnic dimensions,
even where we are not correcting
for the effects
on test scores of educational disadvantage?
What about in that case,
Bree?
If it's that one thing that puts
someone over the edge,
then I guess that would be justifiable.
If everything else about the individual first,
everything they consider about that person's talents
and where they come from
and who they are without these arbitrary factors
is the same.
Without these arbitrary factors, you call it.
But before you were suggesting, Bree,
that race and ethnicity
are arbitrary factors outside the control of the applicants.
True, I would agree with that.
And your general principle is that admissions
shouldn't reward arbitrary factors
over which people have no control.
Right.
All right.
Who else?
Who else would like to?
Thank you both.
Who else would like to get into this?
What do you say?
Well, first of all,
I'm for affirmative action temporarily,
but for two reasons.
First of all,
you have to look at the university's purpose.
It is to educate their students.
And I feel that different races,
people coming from different races
have different backgrounds
and they contribute
differently to the education.
And second of all,
when you say they have equal backgrounds,
that's not true when you look at the broader picture
and you look at slavery.
This is kind of a reparation.
I think affirmative action is a temporary solution
to alleviate history
and the wrongs done to African Americans in particular.
And what's your name?
David.
You say that affirmative action is justified,
at least for now,
as a way of compensating
for past injustice,
the legacy of slavery and segregation.
Right.
Who wants to take on that argument?
We need now a critic of affirmative action.
Yes, go ahead.
I think that what happened in the past
has no bearing on what happens today,
and I think that discriminating based on race
should always be wrong,
whether you're discriminating against
one group or another.
Just because our ancestors did something
doesn't mean that that should have any effect
on what happens with us today.
All right.
Good.
I'm sorry, your name is?
Kate.
All right.
Who has an answer for Kate?
Yes.
I just wanted to comment and say that...
Tell us your name.
My name is Mansour.
Because of slavery, because of past injustices,
today we have a higher proportion of African Americans
who are in poverty,
who face less,
less,
less opportunities than white people.
And so because of slavery 200 years ago,
and because of Jim Crow,
and because of segregation,
today we have injustice based on race.
Kate?
I think that there are differences, obviously,
but the way to fix those differences
is not by some artificial fixing of the result.
You need to fix the problem.
So we need to address differences in education
and differences in upbringing
with programs like Head Start
and giving more funding to lower income schools
rather than trying to just fix the result
so it makes it look like
it's equal when really it isn't.
Yes.
Well, with regard to affirmative action based on race,
I just want to say that white people
have had their own affirmative action in this country
for more than 400 years.
It's called nepotism and quid pro quo.
So there's nothing wrong with correcting the injustice
and discrimination that's been done to black people
for 400 years.
Good.
Tell us...
Wait.
I'm sorry.
Tell us...
Wait.
Tell us your name.
Hannah.
All right.
Who has an answer for Hannah?
And just to add to Hannah's point,
because we need now someone to respond,
Hannah, you could have also mentioned legacy admissions.
Exactly.
I was going to say,
if you disagree with affirmative action,
you should disagree with legacy admission
because it's obvious from looking around here
that there are more white legacies than black legacies
in the history of Harvard University.
And explain what legacy admissions are.
Well, legacy admissions is given to black people.
And so,
if you disagree with the history of Harvard University,
you're giving an advantage to someone
who has an arbitrary privilege of their parent
having attended the university to which they're applying.
All right.
So, a reply for Hannah.
Yes.
In the balcony.
Go ahead.
First of all,
if affirmative action is making up for past injustice,
how do you explain minorities
that were not historically discriminated against
in the United States who get these advantages?
Well,
I think that the first thing is that
we have to be able to argue that affirmative action
perpetuates divisions between the races
rather than achieve the ultimate goal of race
being an irrelevant factor in our society.
And tell us your name.
Danielle.
Hannah.
I disagree with that
because I think that by promoting diversity
in an institution like this,
you further educate all of the students,
especially the white students
who grew up in predominantly white areas.
It's certainly a form of education
to be exposed to people from different backgrounds.
And you put white students at an inherent disadvantage
when you surround them only with the white students.
So,
I think that the first thing
that we have to do is to make sure
that we're not just the white students
who are discriminated against
by the white students.
And I think that's the first thing
that we have to do is to make sure
that we're not just the white students
who are discriminated against
by the white students.
And you put white students
at an inherent disadvantage
when you surround them only with their own kind.
Why should race necessarily
be equated with diversity?
There's so many other forms.
Why should we assume
that race makes people different?
Again,
that's perpetuating the idea
of racial division
within our universities
and our society.
Hannah.
With regard to African American people
being given a special advantage,
it's obvious that they bring something special
to the table
because they have a unique perspective
just as someone from a different religion
or socioeconomic background would as well.
As you say,
there are many different types of diversity.
There's no reason that racial diversity
should be eliminated from that criteria.
Yes, go ahead.
Racial discrimination is illegal in this country,
and I believe that it was African American leaders
themselves when Martin Luther King said
he wanted to be judged
not on the color of his skin
but by the content of his character,
his merit, his achievements.
And I just think that to decide
solely based on someone's race
is just inherently unfair.
I mean, if you want to correct
based on disadvantaged backgrounds,
that's fine,
but there are also disadvantaged white people as well.
It shouldn't matter if you're white or white.
Tell us your name.
Ted.
Ted?
Yes.
Think of Hopwood.
It's unfair to count race
or I assume you would also say ethnicity or religion?
Yes.
Do you think she has a right to be considered
according to her grades and test scores?
No, there is more to it than that.
You need to...
Universities need to promote diversity.
So you agree with the goal of promoting diversity?
There's ways to promote diversity
besides discriminating against people
solely based on a factor that they cannot control.
All right, so what makes it wrong
is that she can't control her race.
She can't control the fact that she's white.
That's the heart of the unfairness to her.
Bree made a similar point,
that basing admissions on factors that people can't control
is fundamentally unfair.
What do you say?
There's a lot of things you can't control,
and if you're going to
go through it based on merit,
like just based on your test scores,
a lot of what you can achieve
has to do with the family background that you raised.
If both your parents were scholarly,
then you have more of a chance
of actually being more scholarly yourself
and getting those grades.
And you can't control what
kind of family background you have.
You can't control your grades.
You can't control what kind
of family you were born into.
All right, good.
That's a great rejoinder.
What's your name?
答
Da.
Ted, are you against advantages that
come from the family you were born into?
What about legacy admissions?
I mean, I do believe that
in terms of a legacy admission,
you shouldn't have a special preference.
I mean, there is a legacy admission you could argue
is another part of diversity.
You could say it's important to have
a small percentage of people that
have a several generation family attendance
at a place like Harvard.
However, that should not be an advantaged factor like race.
That should just be another part of promoting diversity.
Should it count at all?
I think that alumni status,
should it count at all, Ted?
Yes, it should count.
All right, I want to step back for a moment
from these arguments.
Thank you all for these contributions.
We're going to come back to you.
If you've listened carefully, I think
you will have noticed three different arguments
emerged from this discussion in defense
of considering race and ethnicity as a factor in admissions.
One argument has to do with correcting
for the effects of educational disadvantage.
That was Anisha's argument.
This is what we might call the corrective argument.
Correcting for differences in educational background,
the kind of school people
went to, the opportunities they had,
and so on.
That's one argument.
What's worth noticing, though, is that that argument
is consistent in principle with the idea
that only academic promise and scholarly potential
should count in admissions.
We just need to go
beyond test scores and grades alone
to get a true estimate of academic success.
Thank you.
And that's the first argument.
Then we heard a second argument that said affirmative action
is justified even where there may not
be the need to correct for educational disadvantage
in a particular applicant's case.
It's justified as a way of compensating for past wrongs,
for historic injustices.
So that's a compensatory
argument, compensating for past wrongs.
Then we heard a third,
a different argument for affirmative action
from Hannah and others that
argued in the name of diversity.
Now, the diversity argument is
different from the compensatory argument
because it makes a certain appeal to the social purpose
or the social mission of the college or university.
There are really two aspects to the diversity argument.
One says it's important to have a diverse student body
for the sake of the educational experience for everyone.
Hannah made that point.
And the other talks about the wider society.
This was the argument made by the university.
Thank you.
This was the argument made by the
University of Texas in the Hopwood case.
We need to train lawyers
and judges and leaders, public officials,
who will contribute to the strength, the civic strength,
of the state of Texas
and the country as a whole.
So there are two different
aspects to the diversity argument.
But both are arguments in
the name of the social purpose
or the social mission or the common good.
Served by the institution.
Well, what about the force of these arguments?
We've also heard objections to these arguments.
The most powerful objection to the compensatory argument is,
is it fair to ask Cheryl
Hopwood today to make the sacrifice,
to pay the compensation for
an injustice that was admittedly committed
and was egregious in the past,
but in which she was not implicated?
Is that fair?
So that's an important
objection to the compensatory argument.
And in order to meet that objection,
we would have to investigate
whether there is such a thing
as group rights or collective
responsibility that reaches over time.
So having identified that issue,
let's set it aside to turn to the diversity argument.
The diversity argument doesn't have
to worry about that question,
about collective responsibility for past wrongs.
Because it says, for reasons Hannah and others pointed out,
that the common good is served, is advanced,
if there is a racially and ethnically diverse student body.
Everyone benefits.
And this indeed was the argument that Harvard made
when it filed a friend of
the court brief to the Supreme Court
in the 1978 case, affirmative action case, the Bakke case.
And the Harvard brief, the Harvard rationale,
was cited by Justice Powell,
who was the swing vote
in the case, upholding affirmative action.
He cited that as providing the rationale that he thought,
was constitutionally acceptable.
Harvard's argument in its brief was this.
We care about diversity.
Scholarly excellence alone has never
been the criterion of admission,
the sole criterion of admission to Harvard College.
Fifteen years ago, diversity meant students from California,
and New York, and Massachusetts.
City dwellers and farm boys,
violinists, painters, and football players,
biologists, historians, and classicists.
The only difference now, Harvard argued,
is that we're adding racial and ethnic status
to this long list of diversity considerations.
When reviewing the large number of candidates
able to do well in our classes, Harvard wrote,
race may count as a plus,
just as coming from Iowa may count,
being a good middle linebacker, or pianist.
A farm boy from Idaho
can bring something to Harvard College
that a Bostonian cannot offer.
Similarly, a black student can usually bring something
a white student cannot offer.
The quality of the educational experience of all students
depends in part on these differences
in the background and outlook that students bring with them.
That was Harvard's argument.
Now what about the diversity argument?
Is it persuasive?
If it's to be persuasive, it
has to meet one very powerful objection
that we've heard voiced here,
by Ted, by Bree.
Unless you're a utilitarian,
you believe that individual rights can't be violated.
And so the question is,
is there an individual right that is violated?
Is Cheryl Hopwood's right violated
if she is used, so to speak,
denied admission,
for the sake of the
common good and the social mission
that the University of Texas
Law School has defined for itself?
Does she have a right?
Don't we deserve to be considered,
according to our excellences, our achievements,
our hard work?
Isn't that the right at stake?
Now we've already heard an answer to that argument.
No, she doesn't have a right.
Nobody deserves to be admitted.
Notice how this gets us back
to the issue of desert versus entitlement.
They're arguing there is no
individual right that Hopwood has.
She doesn't deserve to be admitted
according to any particular set of criteria
that she believes to be important,
including criteria that have only to do
with her efforts and achievements.
Why not?
I think implicit in this argument
is something like Rawls's rejection of moral desert
as the basis of distributive justice.
Yes, once Harvard defines its mission
and designs its admission
policy in the light of its mission,
people are entitled, who fit those criteria,
they are entitled to be admitted.
But according to this argument,
no one deserves that Harvard College
define its mission and design its admission criteria
in the first place in
a way that prizes the qualities
they happen to have in abundance.
Whether those qualities are test scores or grades
or the ability to play the piano
or to be a good middle linebacker
or to come from Iowa
or to come from a certain minority group.
So you see how this debate about affirmative action,
especially the diversity argument,
takes us back to the question of rights,
which in turn takes us back to the question
of whether moral desert is or is not
the basis for distributive justice.
Think about that over the weekend
and we'll continue this discussion next time.
Suppose we're distributing flutes.
Who should get the best ones?
What's Aristotle's answer?
Anyone.
His answer is the best flutes
should go to the best flute players
because that's what flutes are.
And that's what we're for.
When we ended last time,
we were considering arguments
for and against affirmative action,
counting race as a factor in admissions.
And in the course of the discussion,
three arguments emerged,
three arguments for affirmative action.
One of them was the idea
that race and ethnic background should count
as a way of correcting for
the true meaning of test scores and grades.
Getting a more accurate measure
of the academic potential those scores,
those numbers represent.
Second was what we called the compensatory argument.
The argument was that,
the idea of righting past wrongs,
past injustice.
And the third was the diversity argument.
And when Cheryl Hopwood,
in the 1990s,
challenged the University of Texas Law School's
affirmative action program
in the federal courts,
the University of Texas made another version
of the diversity argument,
saying that the broader social purpose,
the social mission of the University of Texas Law School,
is to produce leaders
in the legal community,
in the political community,
among judges,
lawyers,
legislators,
and therefore it's important that we produce leaders
who reflect the background and the experience
and the ethnic and the racial composition
of the state of Texas.
It's important for serving our wider social mission.
That was the University of Texas Law School's argument.
And then we considered an objection
to the diversity argument,
which after all is an argument in the name of
the social mission,
the common good.
We saw that Rawls does not simply believe
that arguments of the common good
or the general welfare should prevail
if individual rights must be violated
in the course of promoting the common good.
You remember that was the question,
the challenge,
to the diversity rationale that we were considering
when we finished last time.
And we began to discuss the question,
well, what right might be at stake?
Maybe the right to be considered,
according to factors within one's control.
Maybe this is the argument that Cheryl Hopwood
implicitly was making.
She can't help the fact that she's white.
Why should her chance at getting into law school
depend on a factor she can't control?
And then Hannah,
who was advancing an argument,
last time,
said,
Harvard has the right
to define its mission
any way it wants to.
It's a private institution.
And it's only once Harvard defines its mission
that we can identify
the qualities that count.
So no rights are being violated.
Now,
what about that argument?
What I would like to do is to hear objections
to that reply,
and then see whether others have an answer.
Yes.
And tell us your name.
Da.
Right.
You spoke up last time.
All right.
How do you answer that argument?
Well, I think there was two things in there.
One of them was that a private institution
could define its mission however it wants.
But then that doesn't make however it defines it right.
Like, I could define my personal mission as,
I want to collect all the money in the world.
But does that make it even a good mission?
So you can't, like,
you can't say that just because
a college is a private institution,
it could just define it whatever it wants.
We still have to think about
what are the ways defining it is right.
And in the case of affirmative action,
a lot of people have said that
since there's a lot of other factors involved,
we could, why not race?
Like, if we already know that the system is imperfect.
All right.
I want to stick with your first point, Da.
Here's Da's objection.
Can a college,
or university,
define its social purpose any way it wants to,
and then define admissions criteria accordingly?
What about the University of Texas Law School,
not today,
but in the 1950s?
Then there was another Supreme Court case
against the admissions policy
of the University of Texas Law School,
because it was segmented
and segregated.
It only admitted whites.
And when the case went
to court back in the 50s,
the University of Texas Law School
also invoked its mission.
Our mission as a law school
is to educate lawyers
for the Texas bar,
for Texas law firms.
And no Texas law firm
hires African Americans.
So to fulfill our mission,
we only admit whites.
Or consider Harvard
in the 1930s,
when it had
anti-Jewish quotas.
President Lowell,
president of Harvard in the 1930s, said
that he had nothing personally against Jews,
but he invoked the mission,
the social purpose of Harvard,
he said,
which is not only to train intellectuals.
Part of the mission of Harvard,
he said,
is to train stockbrokers for Wall Street,
presidents and senators.
And there are very few Jews
who go into those professions.
Now, here's the challenge.
Is there a principle distinction
between the invocation
of the social purpose
of the college or university today
in the diversity rationale
and the invocation of the social purpose
or mission of the university
by Texas in the 1950s
or Harvard in the 1930s?
Is there a difference in principle?
What's the reply?
Hannah?
Well, I think that the principle is,
basically,
the distinction between inclusion versus exclusion.
I think that it's morally wrong of the university
to say,
we're going to exclude you
on the basis of your religion or your race.
That's denial on the basis of arbitrary factors.
What Harvard is trying to do today
with its diversity initiatives
is to include groups that were excluded in the past.
Good.
Let's see if,
stay there.
Let's see if someone would like to reply.
So,
I think that the principle
of the
Good.
So, the element of malice
is that in the historic segregationist,
racist, anti-Semitic quotas or prohibitions,
there was built into them
a certain kind of malice,
a certain kind of judgment
that African Americans or Jews
were somehow less worthy than everybody else.
Whereas present day affirmative action programs
don't involve or imply any such,
judgment.
What it amounts to saying is,
so long as a policy
just uses people in a way
as valuable to the social purpose
of the institution,
it's okay,
provided it doesn't judge them
maliciously as Stevie might add,
as intrinsically less worthy.
I'd like to raise a question.
Doesn't that concede
that all of us,
when we compete for positions,
or for seats in colleges and universities,
in a way,
are being used,
not judged,
but used
in a way that has nothing to do
with the moral,
moral,
moral virtue
with moral
because we need that to be
a moral virtue?
Yes.
Honest.
Isso dá sentido
whether it's positions or places in
the class or income and wealth,
is a matter of moral desert.
Suppose that were the moral
basis of Harvard's admissions policy.
What letters would they have to write
to people they rejected or accepted for that matter?
Wouldn't they have to write something like this?
Dear unsuccessful applicant,
we regret to inform you that
your application for admission has been rejected.
It's not your fault that when you came along,
society happened not to need
the qualities you had to offer.
Those admitted instead of you are
not themselves deserving of a place,
nor worthy of praise for the
factors that led to their admission.
We are in any case only using them and you
as instruments of a wider social purpose.
Better luck next time.
What was the letter you
actually got when you were admitted?
Perhaps it should have read something like this.
Dear successful applicant,
we are pleased to inform you that
your application for admission has been accepted.
It turns out, lucky for you,
that you have the traits
that society needs at the moment,
so we propose to exploit
your assets for society's advantage.
You've done it.
It's the truth.
are to be congratulated. Not in the sense
that you deserve credit for having the qualities
that led to your admission, but only in the
sense that the winner of the lottery is to
be congratulated. And if you choose to
accept our offer, you will ultimately be entitled
to the benefits that attach to being used
in this way. We look forward to seeing you
in the fall. Now, there is something a
little odd, morally odd. If it's true that you're
not going to be able to get a ticket
to the Olympics, it's true that those letters do
reflect the theory, the philosophy underlying the
policy. So here's the question they pose.
And it's a question that takes us back
to a big issue in political philosophy. Is it
possible and is it desirable to detach
questions of desire from the political philosophy? And
what have you learned from all of these conversations?
Well, we'll first tell Mr.
Regidor of what he knows best.
If you had only a不会.
Well, I'm happy to do that, but I forgot to
turn to Mr. lugar on the topic of fair play here,
since I knew that we all
had protests going on out there.
that the incentive, the reason he
had for detaching distributive justice from moral
desert was an egalitarian one. That if we
set desert to one side, there's greater scope
for the exercise of egalitarian considerations.
The veil of ignorance, the two principles,
the difference principle, helping the least
well off, redistribution and all that. But
what's interesting is if you look at
a range of thinkers we've been considering, there
does seem to be a reason they want
to detach justice from desert that goes well beyond
any concern for equality. Libertarian rights
oriented theorists of the kind we've been
studying, as well as egalitarian rights
oriented theorists, including Rawls, and others, are
all agree, despite their disagreements over
distributive justice and the welfare state
and all of that, they all agree that justice
is not a matter of rewarding or honoring virtue
or moral desert. Now why do they all
think that? It can't just be for egalitarian reasons,
not all of them.
Okay.
Well, so the problem here is I
see a lack of on each side.
Um,
Portugal
Actually seeing this,
ope u
U
e
o
to
their shared assumption, we need to turn
to a thinker, to a philosopher who disagrees
with them, who explicitly ties justice to
honor, honoring virtue, and merit, and moral
desert. And that thinker is Aristotle. Now,
in many ways, Aristotle's idea of justice
is intuitively very powerful. In some ways, it's
strange. I want to bring out both its
power, its plausibility, and its strangeness so that
we can see what's at stake in this
whole debate about justice and whether it's tied
to desert and virtue. So, what is Aristotle's
answer to the question about justice? For
Aristotle, justice is a matter of honor, honor,
honor, of giving people what they deserve,
giving people their due. It's a matter of
figuring out the proper fit between persons
with their virtues and their appropriate social
roles. Well, what does this picture of justice
look like, and how does it differ from the
conception that seems to be shared
among libertarian and egalitarian rights-oriented theorists
alike? Justice means giving each person his
or her due, giving people what they deserve.
But what is a person's due? What are
the relevant grounds of merit or desert? Aristotle says
that depends on the sort of things
being distributed. Justice involves two factors-things and the
persons to whom the things are assigned. In
general, we say that a person gives away speech,
which can be used for religious purposes. And
that's a piece of evidence. So that also maintains
that coke taxes were wrong, that it's really
the creating of common roots in justice that
really made things worse. And even though you
could look at our time and say, Massacre, you're
looking at some brilliant,ashi , you know,
everyone's saying this, and even more greater minimizing
them, and禁ed them. There's so much in it that
we hate and don'tlaş we mean to deny of that.
In general, we say, Aristotle writes, that persons who
are equal should have equal things assigned to them.
But here there arises a hard question.
Equals in what respects?
Aristotle says, that depends on
the sort of thing we're distributing.
Suppose we're distributing flutes.
What is the relevant merit
or basis of dessert for flutes?
Who should get the best ones?
What's Aristotle's answer?
Anyone?
The best flute players, right.
Those who are best in the
relevant sense, the best flute players.
Is it just to discriminate in allocating flutes?
Yes.
All justice involved.
All is discrimination, Aristotle says.
What matters is that the discrimination
be according to the relevant excellence.
According to the virtue appropriate to having flutes.
He says it would be unjust
to discriminate on some other basis.
In giving out the flutes.
Say, wealth.
Just giving the best flutes to the people who can,
pay the highest price.
Or nobility of birth.
Just giving flutes to aristocrats.
Or physical beauty.
Giving the best flutes to the most handsome.
Or chance, having a lottery.
Aristotle says, birth and beauty may be greater
goods than the ability to play the flute.
And those who possess them may surpass the flute player more
in these qualities than he surpasses them in his flute playing.
But the fact remains that he is the
person who ought to get the best flute.
It's a strange idea, this comparison by the way.
That, I mean, could you say, am I
more handsome than she is a good lacrosse player?
It's a strange kind of comparison.
But putting that aside, Aristotle says, we're not
looking for the best overall, whatever that might mean.
We're looking for the best.
The best musician.
Now why, this is important to see, why should
the best flutes go to the best flute players?
Well, why do you think?
Anybody?
What?
They'll produce the best music, well,
and everybody will enjoy it more.
That's not Aristotle's answer.
Aristotle is not a utilitarian.
He's not just saying, that way there will be better
music and everyone will enjoy it, everyone will be better off.
His answer is, the best flutes should go to
the best flute players because that's what flutes are for.
To be played well.
The purpose of flute playing, the
purpose is to produce excellent music.
And those who can best perfect that
purpose, ought properly to have the best ones.
Now it may also be true, as a welcome
side effect, that everyone will enjoy listening to that music.
So, that answer is true
enough as far as it goes.
But it's important to see that
Aristotle's reason is not a utilitarian reason.
It's a reason that looks, here's where
you might think it's a little bit strange.
It looks to the purpose, the
point, the goal of flute playing.
Another way of describing this, looking to
the goal to determine the just allocation.
The Greek for goal or end was telos.
So Aristotle says, you have to consider the point, the end, the
goal, the telos of the thing, in this case of flute playing.
And that's how you define
a just allocation, a just discrimination.
So this idea of reasoning from the
goal, from the telos, is called teleological reasoning.
Teleological moral reasoning.
And that's Aristotle's way.
Reasoning from the goal, from the end.
Now this may seem, as I said, a strange idea.
That we're supposed to reason from the purpose.
But it is, does have a certain intuitive plausibility.
Consider the allocation, let's say at Harvard,
of the best tennis courts or squash courts.
How should they be allocated?
Who should have priority in playing on the best courts?
Well, you might say, those
who can play the best tennis.
Those who can best afford them.
Set up a fee system.
Charge money for them.
Aristotle would say no.
You might say, well, Harvard big
shots, the most influential people at Harvard.
Who would they be?
The senior faculty should have priority.
In playing on the best tennis courts.
No, Aristotle would reject that.
Some scientist may be a greater scientist than
some varsity tennis player is a tennis player.
But still the tennis player is the one who should
have priority for the best, playing on the best tennis court.
There is a certain intuitive plausibility to this idea.
Now, one of the things that makes it strange is that
in Aristotle's world, in the ancient world, it wasn't only social practices.
That were governed, in Aristotle's view,
by teleological reasoning and teleological explanation.
All of nature was understood to be a meaningful order.
And what it meant to understand nature, to grasp nature, to find our place within
nature, was to inquire into and read out the purposes or the telos of nature.
And with the advent of modern science, it's
been difficult to think of the world that way.
And so it makes it harder, perhaps,
to think of justice in a teleological way.
But there is a certain naturalness to thinking
about even the natural world as teleologically ordered.
As a purpose of whole.
In fact, children have to be educated out
of this way of looking at the world.
I realized this when I was a young boy.
I was a teenager.
I realized this when my kids were very
young and I was reading them a book.
Winnie the Pooh.
And Winnie the Pooh gives you a great idea of how there is
a certain natural childlike way of looking at the world in a teleological way.
You may remember a story of Winnie
the Pooh walking in the forest one day.
And from the top of a
tree there came a loud buzzing noise.
Winnie the Pooh sat at the foot of the tree,
put his head between his paws and began to think.
Here's what he said to himself.
That buzzing noise means something.
You don't get a buzzing noise like that,
just buzzing and buzzing, without its meaning something.
If there's a buzzing noise,
somebody's making a buzzing noise.
And the only reason for making a buzzing noise that
I know of, is because somebody's making a buzzing noise.
If you know a buzzing noise that
I know of, is because you're a bee.
Then he thought for another long time and said...
And the only reason for being a
bee that I know of, is making honey.
And then he got up and he said...
And the only reason for making
honey is so I can eat it.
This is an example of teleological reasoning.
It isn't so implausible after all.
Now, we grow up and
we're talked out of this way,
of thinking about the world.
But here's the question.
Even if teleological explanations are not so important,
even if teleological explanations
don't fit with modern science,
even if we've outgrown them in understanding nature,
isn't there something still
intuitively and morally plausible,
even powerful, about Aristotle's idea that
the only way to think about justice
is to reason from the purpose, the
goal, the telos of the social practice,
and isn't that precisely what we're talking about?
That's not what we were doing
when we were disagreeing about affirmative action.
You could almost recast that disagreement
as one about what the proper, appropriate purpose or end
of a university education consists in.
Reasoning from the purpose or from
the telos or from the end,
Aristotle says that's indispensable
to thinking about justice.
Is he right?
Think about that question as
you turn to Aristotle's politics.
Teach Aristotle to discuss counsel within your own
so it becomes clear that there are others and, somehow,
Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...